

Greater Hobart Region, Tasmania, Australia September 2023

☐ +61 466 683 552 | ▼toddellis.wa@gmail.com | ☐ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | ☑ q6vTAroAAAAJ | ☑ Todd-Ellis-4 | otoddellis | in tmichaelellis

### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I'm a data analyst and early career researcher with a varied background in forest ecology, pyrogeography, climate change, geospatial science, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst and researcher in a variety of laboratory, field, and office settings throughout the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers in institutional policies and procedures, as well as methodological approaches to statistical analysis; and managed both complex and transformative projects for higher education, government agencies, and private industry. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

As at 2023-09-26, I have 3 peer-reviewed publications including 2 first-author publications. I have received a total of 53 or 69 citations with an h-index of 3 or 3 based on Scopus and Google Scholar, respectively.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences**

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania

2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

#### Master of Science, Geography

Bellingham, WA, USA

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

2013 - 2016

- · Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

#### **Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography and Geology**

San Marcos, TX, USA

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

2007 - 2012

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### **Data Insights Analyst**

**Data Analyst** 

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (full-time)

2023-01 - present

- Managing the development and implementation of a transformative statewide program to improve equity of access to higher education
- · Leading the development of statistical models and reporting tools for managing offers and course quotas
- Streamlining and automating the higher education admissions system for school leavers
- Providing insights and consultations to institutional and external stakeholders

# **Adjunct Researcher**

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - 2023-03

- · Developed complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- · Oversaw multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- Managed custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- · Collaborated with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

## University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2021-02 - 2023-01

- Developed statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managed design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- Designed and implemented programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- Oversaw development of internal reporting and statistical packages

	Williamson, G.J., Ellis, T.M., and Bowman, D.M.J.S. (2022). Double-Differenced dNBR: Combining MODIS and	
1	Landsat Imagery to Map Fine-Grained Fire Mosaics in Lowland Eucalyptus Savanna in Kakadu National Park,	3 citation
_	Northern Australia. <i>Fire</i> , 5(5), 160. doi:10.3390/fire5050160	
	<b>Ellis, T.M.</b> , Bowman, D.M.J.S., Jain, P., Flannigan, M.D., and Williamson, G.J. (2022). Global increase in	
2	wildfire risk due to climate-driven declines in fuel moisture. <i>Global Change Biology</i> , 28(4), 1544-1559.	45 citation
	doi:10.1111/gcb.16006	
	Ellis, T.M., and Flower, A. (2017). A multicentury dendrochronological reconstruction of western spruce	
3	budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands, northeastern Washington. Canadian Journal of Forest	5 citation
	Research, 47(9), 1266-1277. doi:10.1139/cjfr-2016-0399	
CONS	ULTING	
RESEAR	СН	
2020-08	Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery	AUDĆ1 00
	Frontier Development Lab	AUD\$1,00
2019-06	Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity	USD\$2,50
	USDA Forest Service	00042,00
2018-08	Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate	USD\$2,50
	USDA Forest Service	. ,
MANUS	CRIPT REVIEWER	
	Climatic Change (since 2023-06)	
	Earth's Future (since 2022-09)	
	Fire Ecology (since 2019-01)	
	Global Change Biology (since 2022-10)	
	New Phytologist (since 2022-11)	
HONG	OURS	
GRANTS	S, SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS	
2023-09	Student Services and Operations (SSO) Division Student Focus Award	AUD\$5
	University of Tasmania	710093
2022-11	Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Award	AUD\$5
	University of Tasmania	
2021-10	NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research	AUD\$10,00
2020.00	Australian Museum	
2020-08	Bushfire Data Quest 2020 Frontier Development Lab	AUD\$1,00
2019-09	Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)	
2015-05	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	AUD\$28,000 p.d
2019-09	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)	
	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	AUD\$5,000 p.d

# CONFERENCES AND PRESENTATIONS

2022-12	Removing Barriers and transforming access to tertiary education: The Schools Recommendation Program in Tasmania	Macquarie Park, NSW
	Australasian Association for Institutional Research Forum 2022	
2022-06	Dynamic mapping and analysis of fire regimes, past, present, and future	Wollongong, NSW
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Showcase 2022 (poster)	
2021-05	Fuel moisture trend tool	Wollongong, NSW
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2021 (poster)	
2020-03	Changes in moisture availability drive fire risk	Wollongong, NSW
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2020 (presentation)	